Tyler Long

Data Analyst

Nashville, TN (248) 318 - 1391

tyler.derek.long@gmail.com LinkedIn Profile GitHub Portfolio

Successful Grant Compliance Manager with 5 years of professional experience. Realizing skills improvement was essential to manage and communicate grant compliance, this driven self-starter and fast learner explored classes in SQL and Python through Coursera, which led to enrolling in the Data Analytics training provided by Nashville Software School. Seeking a career change to a position focused on data analytics and performance reporting for a medium to large non-profit.

Professional Experience

Data Analytics Apprentice | Nashville Software School | Nashville, TN July 2022 – Present

Intensive full-time bootcamp focusing on data analytics fundamentals and problem solving. Used real-world datasets and included projects where findings were presented to stakeholders from the community.

- Source code version control with Git/GitHub to manage the following projects:
- Lahman Baseball with SQL: Interactive class assignment where students collaborated to analyze and answer questions using baseball statistics from 1876 2016. Query prompts focused extensively on combining CTEs, subqueries, and joins to explore a wealth of statistics. I practiced on this dataset to build additional skills covered in the course, such as window functions and query ranking.
- Davidson County Traffic Accidents with Power BI: Project designed to create a dashboard to promote public safety. This assignment focused on selecting the appropriate graph according to data measures and dimensions. My final product displayed stacked bar, pie, and line charts to summarize total accidents per precinct according to collision type. I included slicers to add interactivity and filtering during presentation to the class.
- United Nations GDP and Internet Usage with Python, Pandas, Matplotlib: Project using United Nations data to evaluate correlations between gross domestic product and internet usage per capita. This project covered a wide range of Python libraries and replied heavily on Google searches and help from peers to answer question prompts and arrange data frames. Findings were presented using the matplotlib and seaborn libraries.
- Nashville City Cemetery with Excel: Project to analyze burial data from 1850 1970 to spark public interest and increase visitation rates. To support this campaign, students analyzed most common causes of death according to year, broken down by age, race, gender, and location. This challenging project relied heavily on data cleaning and string manipulation before findings were presented using pivot charts and slicers.

Motions Clerk | Davidson County Chancery Court | Nashville, TN April 2022 – Present

- Review, approve case motions prior to upload into the county's database
- Monitor volume of motions and related hearing dates, update Calendar Clerk of any changes to the motion docket
- Respond to inquiries by attorneys and the public
- Assist customers who require assistance in Spanish

Compliance Manager | TN Department of Labor, Workforce Development | Nashville, TN July 2016 – March 2022

- Designed, implemented, and maintained the State's monitoring system—using Excel—to track key performance indicators for participant eligibility to receive WIOA Title I and Re-Employment Services Eligibility Assessment program services, reported quarterly.
- Served as the primary point of contact to troubleshoot, update, and resolve problems for the participant eligibility review tools. Primary point of contact to clarify incorrect or inconsistent queries when generating review samples from database.
- Reported performance metrics and compliance status to the State Workforce Development Board, County Mayors, and executive-level staff that support the Local Workforce Development Boards.
- Analyzed non-compliance findings and resolution procedures to ensure state policies remained in compliance with federal and state regulations that govern awards spent on local workforce development activities.
- Collaborated with Finance and Administration staff to ensure sub-recipients of grant funding satisfactorily resolved findings identified during on-site monitoring reviews that identified misappropriated funds or funds reported outside acceptable reporting parameters.

Education and Certificates

Bachelor of Arts | University of Illinois, Chicago | Chicago, IL Data Analytics Certificate | Nashville Software School | January 2023 Python for Everybody | University of Michigan | May, June 2022 Excel Skills for Business | Macquarie University | June 2021

Spanish Language Proficiency

- Servicio Internacional de Evaluación de la Lengua Española (SIELE)
- The exam demonstrates broad working proficiency, defined as the ability to interact with a degree of fluency and spontaneity that makes regular interaction with native speakers possible without strain for either party.